[Music]
welcome to this watch new in Excel
layouts for developers session in the
2024 wave
1 in this session I'm going to talk to
you about reporting capabilities in the
new wave so we're going to talk about
the way to develop translatable reports
how to call business Central apis from
Excel reports then I'm going to show you
a preview of one of the new Excel
reports that ship with business Central
as an example of how all this works and
then finally a bit of preview on Excel
copilot on business Central data so
let's get
started translatable Excel reports is
something that you will only need if
you're an isv I assume and Microsoft we
are an isv and for us to ship Excel
reports we we needed these to be
multilanguage so back in 23
23.3 we added the ability or we added um
two Excel layouts that we always have a
hidden worksheet with some extra static
and runtime metadata so we now show you
I can show you here uh this worksheet
with um for static
metadata uh things from the report
object itself so things like what's
what's extension does it come from blah
blah blah most importantly for you as a
report uh layout designer is the three
things about this report title about
this report text and uh the report help
link because this gives you if the
report designer or the report objects uh
developer added this metadata uh for the
teaching tip title and text and for the
report uh context specific help link you
can actually use this in the Excel
report itself if you want to provide
like context specific help uh maybe a
worksheet stating about this report you
can put that in there the second thing
that that is you very useful from this
worksheet is the request properties now
not the request page but the actual
report requests so this is where we now
store the tenant ID environment name
type and company name and Company
ID and the date for when this report was
run and you can use this either in the
layout itself for instance when the
report was uh was run the date time for
that you can put it in in the layout so
that when people run the report they can
see when it was refreshed or when it was
run uh but refresh is also a new thing
here uh because if you and I'll show you
some examples of that the company or the
environment name and the company name or
Company ID can be used in apis so that
you can refresh the data or you can
augment the report data set with
additional data from business Central
apis
then in 23.3 we also added um a caption
data worksheet both with include caption
on columns in the in the in the data
items in the report data set as well as
any labels that you add in the label
section of the report object is now uh
transferred into this worksheet so that
you have all the
captions uh from uh from the the report
object available in your when you lay
out and of course these will then
be uh populated the caption uh will be
copulated with values uh when the user
actually runs the
report then the final part of this the
most important part also in version
23.3 is that we added the ability to
translate all of this uh at runtime so
as a report author you can now use
translation tags or dollar dollar for
worksheet names for chart headers for
pivot elements slicer headers and so on
um when you layout the Excel and when
you then upload and when people run the
report with with this Excel layout the
server will then replace these tags with
values so that the the report is
translated to the language of the user
when they ran the
report as a final thing we also added
what we called userdefined translation
data worksheet which means that in case
you have texts or strings that you would
like to be in the layout but they are
not present in the report object itself
as captions there you can add them to
the translation data worksheet in the
layout with the different languages
available so for instance my layout
Title Here is available in four
different languages Danish us English um
German and French and then uh depending
on if the user when they run the report
have one of these four uh that would be
then be translated so you can now Supply
strings to the report layout that are
not present as captions so let's see an
example of how this works on the left I
have uh added the layout with this
dollar dollar syntax and you can see
four different things there a cell that
is going to be translated on the upper
left there's the worksheet name there
are the names on the slicers and then
there is the title in the chart so when
the user runs the report uh in this case
in this example it's a user that used
Danish language you can see that the the
cill is translated you can see that the
slicer titles are translated to to
Danish you can see the um the chart
title is translated and finally that the
worksheet is translated as well to
conclude this means that if you are a
VAR just adding um an Excel report or a
report with Excel layouts for German
customers there's no need for this but
if you are an icv or if you are if you
if you work with customers that operate
in multiple countries where it's
important that they the users get the
Excel reports in their own language then
this is for you uh to to use it's
already present in version
23.3 but now this is the first time we
we we talk about it in the launch
event all right I mentioned that um the
new worksheet that was added in version
23.3 enables
refreshable uh Excel
reports if only you you uh you load the
data in Excel not from the report data
set but using apis and using power query
so how how could that such a thing
work remember that when you call
business Central apis the the uis for
these always have a structure that looks
like this Su URL API blah blah blah D V2
Dash environment name- API and so on and
then after this prefix of the URI comes
the actual uh API that always starts
with a company with an identifier and
then the actual API you call this means
that you need two two things you need
the environment name and you need the
company ident ID uh to be able to
construct such a
URI and the good thing is the these are
now exactly these two uh pieces of
information are available uh on the new
report metadata worksheet the
environment name and the company ID also
the company name this means that if you
open a new query in power quer in Excel
uh of type O data and just uh maybe just
put in a legal o data feed uh in there
then after the fact you can open the
advant editor and instead of the the URL
that for instance this URL always works
that you can see here you can start
constructing the the the URI for the API
you want to call by referring to the
worksheet uh with these two and now
suddenly you have a power query query
that that reads from business Central
API but using the environment name and
the company when people run the report
this means that you can actually in Cas
if you think of it if you want to you
can scale down the data set in the
report object to something super simple
like maybe nothing almost and then the
all the data loading you can do that in
power CR from apis if you do that then
refreshing the data set from uh in Excel
you will then just refresh the data from
the apis
with version uh 24 with this new version
uh we also ship new Excel reports in the
base
application uh out of the box and uh
these are added to the uh business
manager role Center and accountant role
Center on uh on here on Excel uh reports
you can see them with uh with their
names parenthesis preview um or you can
also search for preview on the report or
role Explorer um and then they would
show up
there they are in preview for because we
still need to maybe tweak a few things
it's not that they're not showing the
right amount of data or the right data
but it could be that we want to tweak
the design a little bit uh learn from
users how they use these but you as
developer can also use these seven new
reports to kind of get a look and feel
of how to code this new way of doing
translatable reports or maybe using
power query or power power U model
things in power query or power pivot in
Excel so let's take a look at one of
these and uh just to give you an idea
and then you can explore at your own
pace um with the the rests of these
seven reports Let's uh let's have a look
at one of these new Excel reports right
so I here I'm I'm on the business
manager Road Center and and you can see
this menu Excel reports have the Legacy
reports that will likely be deprecated
in a later version and then these new
preview reports that you should go take
a look at and what's better than take a
look at what people owe me right I want
to make sure I improve my cash flow so
I'll take the HED accounts receivables
report and there's nothing new to this
request page is just click download
because that's the the way we deal with
Excel of course if actually a pro tip
here if you demo this with a customer
make sure that you show this with Excel
sorry with one drive integration enabled
because then download will not be
download but actually just open in a new
browser tab but I was not as clever as
you so this downloads the new report and
let me open that and let's have a look
so the first thing you notice is that
you need to enable content this is just
a warning from Excel because we have
some power query in the report there's
no way around it at least not in the
security setting on my computer so I
will click that uh this will enable
things to load in power query inside
Excel and now you can see the the report
as seen from the user has three
different worksheets by period uh you
can see Dimensions it's actually it uh I
can filter on that in these slices uh I
can filter on uh the customer number and
on the customer uh group I can do the
same uh by period here there's now a new
currency code uh I can see that I need
to work on uh this s small bo here
that's fine you can see the dollar
dollar should of course have been
translated and let me have a look at
that after the recording um and then uh
due by currencies again there's there
slicers here and that's the way the Port
looks as seen from the user but we are
developers we want to dive into how
things look under the hood so let me go
here and unhide all the
worksheets that have been
hidden and now I get a little bit more
so translation data this was the user
defined one apparently the developer for
this from this report didn't need that
so this is empty but if for some reason
maybe you add a layout to an exist in
report and you don't have access to
updating that report you can add your
own strings here caption data this is
where you get all the labels and
captions me open make this a little bit
bigger here in Excel so now uh this this
is just populated the value column here
is populated at runtime from the
language I used when I ran the report
and then these are the things you can
you can use in your layout just point to
any of these and uh and do a vook up or
or
similar and then there is a report
parameters um there is the aggregated
metadata here that we talked about with
the with the report uh metadata request
metadata you can see here these are the
options when I ran the report from the
request page and the filters that were
added I'm not sure that's going to be at
least I'm not expert enough to to have
that useful but maybe you are and uh
then I I have the actual data sets so
starting in in version
23.0 there's a new option in in in Excel
uh layouts that can give you each of the
data item the top level data items in
the data set in its own worksheet so you
can see the first worksheet here is
customer aging data this sorry this one
the second one is uh Dimension One and
dimension two uh these are the three top
level data items in that report um so go
check out the the new layouts dissect
them see how what the developer did and
and learn from that uh there might be
some additional data modeling in power
pivot and power CR and some of them so
uh go have fun with that the final part
of this session I don't know if it's so
much developed but I want to give you
kind of a look and feel because and this
is about Excel co-pilot it's is still in
in preview in Excel uh but how you can
think of this or maybe present this to
customers as a different way to do
reporting Excel co-pilot just needs the
raw data set and the good thing about
business Central and Excel is we have at
least two ways for you to get that
there's open in Excel from any list page
will open the raw data and the second
part is um
an ex a report with Excel layout will
also give you the raw data set directly
in Excel so so that's that's that's a
good like business Central leans itself
well into Excel
co-pilot Excel co-pilot you you should
think of this as a way to anal analyze
understand and visualize your data with
a copile experience um so for instance
maybe explore your data using co-pilot
natural language interface for it or
maybe let co-pilot suggest things maybe
look for outliers and other things and
what's better than uh maybe let me show
you an example of how this could look on
some uh some data all right back in
Excel I um I needed a little bit more
data than in the previous example so I
took the accounts payables report the
new also one of the new reports I pumped
up business business Central with some
more data artificial data so that
co-pilot has some food to chew on but
apart from that I don't know what's
going to happen here so let's uh let's
have a look I enable co-pilot on my data
worksheet here vendor aging data 100,000
rows let's have a look and for this to
work by the way must uh be the Excel
workbook must be on one drive so this is
another uh
benefit from enabling integration with
business Central to one drive is that
co-pilot Excel will just work out of the
box when uh when you use Excel uh
layouts okay so co-pilots gives me some
options analyze highlight and I'm
actually interested if co-pilot can help
me analyze this large volume of data so
click analy let's see what happens and
um co-pilot comes with some um
suggestions it could do some total of
things over but I would actually like to
ask it whether it could analyze
something that I'm not good as as a
person as a human and that is looking
for outliers in the data so I will see
uh
find me out
liar and see if uh if copilot can come
up with some maybe fraud detection or
dubious weird transactions that I might
need to look into this is accounts uh
payable so these are my vendors people I
owe money maybe there's something going
on one of them U might I don't know
let's see if there's anything that that
is weird in this data set so we're
analyzing uh analyzing analyzing and
let's see if we can find some outliers
in that data
set actually there is something going on
here so you can see co-pilot here uh
told me that for a particular vendor
number here let me just add it to a new
worksheet and uh see what's going on for
this particular vendor
here there are at least three outliers
with these different different dates so
the uh this date here in 2002 something
going on uh here and here and here are
four transactions that I need to look in
further into it might be totally okay it
might be something that that is uh that
that is weird but at least from the data
set these are outliers that look
suspicious or not normal uh so that that
could be one way for you to or for your
customers to use Excel as a way to
analyze for outliers this is just one
example of co-pilot uh Excel
co-pilot right so of course I mean
co-pilot can only suggest things I will
still need to go check it in business
Central um and have a person in the loop
that's the idea of all AI that it is
something that can suggest thing for us
but we still need to have that person to
uh to be in the loop
anyway we are at the end of the session
just a few learning resources in case
you want to learn more about reasoning
over reporting and when Excel would be a
good choice uh go to
aka.ms BC developer that takes you to
developer docs and under developer docs
there's this new article called
analyzing pivoting and sharing data in
business Central that shows you all the
different types of artifacts for
reporting powerbi Excel data analysis on
list and queries um Excel so on where
like when should you use what and for
whom so go check that out in the article
there what we call the bi triangle which
puts these different tools for different
personas for different analytical
purposes uh where the the the tools
Shine the most so make sure that you
look into and understand the scenarios
for different personas and map these to
Technologies so that you don't just do
excel reporting for everyone for
everything but think carefully where
Excel makes
sense for for end users for your
customers aka.
msbc reporting is the documentation for
for uh for for anything related to bi
and Reporting in the product also here
um how to use Excel uh how to use Excel
reports so um so you can point your
customers to this uh documentation
page if you are the type of person who
want to learn from through examples or
through sample code aka.ms slbc Excel
samples is your friend I will try to my
very best to add new samples to this
when I learn more so that there will be
different reports with different um
Excel layouts that you can what that you
can open up and and play around with and
and learn both uh techniques in Excel
and techniques with um with reports in
business
Central and with that a few Goos start
providing Excel reports for analytics
know the bi triangle if you are an isv
or work in mul have customers who work
in multiple
languages think about how you can
deliver multi language Excel reports in
your apps or in your
Solutions and of course uh start
exploring like with any co-pilot it's a
new thing and you might want to explore
ex Excel co-pilot uh on your own pce so
that you can also learn it uh and maybe
learn it with with
users that's it for this session few
relevant launch event sessions uh if
you're interested in server architecture
this is still kind of server is uh
what's new in Al runtime and database
might be of interest what's new in web
services is also uh server architecture
if you're more into things from a
developer standpoint of course watch new
and visual studio code and Al developer
development is your session but also um
there's a session called
key updates in learning content for
developers that might be of interest as
well uh and also if you do systems
Integrations uh integrating business
Central with other uh systems through
web services there's a new learning
session on a lot of new content for that
so go check that out then to conclude
AKA links uh so take discussions to to
Yammer BC ymer is where we talk about
things that we don't want to have on
social media BC all is the AKA link to
rule them all so go there to find all
the other AKA links that are available
for you as a partner BC ideas is where
you suggest feature improvements and
product improvements um we on social
media X and Linkedin so so join the
conversation there and if you want to
join office hours either live or
recorded sessions BC office hours is the
AKA link that you should have and with
that say thank you than a lot for
joining my session on Excel uh hope you
have a great business Central launch
event thank
you